Guide to the Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company records 1892-1928
Montana Historical Society
Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company records
1892-1928
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 145
Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company
7 linear feet of shelf space
Conrad Kohrs and John Bielenberg operated a ranch at Deer Lodge, Montana. Records (1892-1928) consist of three subgroups: the Kohrs and Bielenberg Subgroup, including correspondence (1913-1920) and financial records (1892-1918) pertaining to the Deer Lodge ranch; the Conrad Kohrs Estate Subgroup (1920-1928), including correspondence of Samuel McKennan, estate executor, and financial records; and the John N.W. Bielenberg Estate Subgroup (1921-1927), including correspondence of executors Samuel McKennan and R.O. Kaufman, court papers, financial records, legal documents, and miscellany.
Carston Conrad Kohrs was born in Wewelsfelth, Holstein, Germany, on August 5, 1835, the son of Carston and Gesche Krause Kohrs. His father, a distiller and brewer, died when Conrad was only seven weeks old. His mother married Claus Bielenberg in 1844. In 1853 Kohrs settled in the United States and learned the meat packing trade. He joined the California gold rush in 1857, and worked a claim near Eureka, before continuing his search for gold on the Frazer River in Canada. He returned to the East, but in 1862 he crossed the plains to Salt Lake, and from there ranged north to the Big Hole and Deer Lodge valleys of what is now Montana. Although he had intended to prospect for gold Kohrs was hired as a butcher and it was in this trade that he found success. He soon began supplying miners and other butchers with meat.
On August 23, 1865, Kohrs bought John Grant's ranch and cattle in the Deer Lodge valley. Kohrs and his half-brother John N. W. Bielenberg are credited with initiating the practice of open-range grazing in central Montana when they moved their herd from Deer Lodge to the Sun River in 1870. By the late 1880s Conrad Kohrs' Pioneer Cattle Company, incorporated in January, 1885, was one of the largest cattle raising operations in the Northwest. In the mid-1910s the Pioneer Cattle Company sold its livestock and retained only the ranches which were run by Bielenberg through the Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company until his death.
Kohrs was also interested in mining. In the spring of 1867 he joined with some partners to form what was to become the Rock Creek Ditch and Mining Company. After locating water rights on Rock Creek, the company constructed a ditch and dam in 1870, and sold water to nearby miners. Kohrs bought another ditch opened by the Atlantic Cable Mining Company in 1868, and began the Pioneer Placer Mining Company near Pioneer in 1870. Ownership of the latter company was transferred to the Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company in 1923.
Kohrs operated the Deer Lodge ranch and many of his business concerns, including his real estate holdings, in partnership with John Bielenberg. The Kohrs and Bielenberg Realty Company was formed in 1906, with Conrad Kohrs, John Bielenberg, and Kohrs' son-in-law O.Y. Warren as directors. A major holding of the Kohrs and Bielenberg Realty Company included the Higgins Block in Missoula. Another Kohrs-owned business was the Conrad Kohrs Company whose assets included the Treacy, Beveridge, Kohrs, Brazier, and Denver blocks in Helena, as well as the Pioneer, Holland, and Robecker ranches and other properties.
By 1908 most of the Kohrs and Bielenberg ranch, mining, and real estate interests were incorporated as the Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company. This holding company was organized in June 1908 with four directors and stockholders: Conrad Kohrs, John Bielenberg, Edward Scharnikow of Deer Lodge, and Conrad's wife Augusta. The Conrad Kohrs Company was a primary stockholder. Samuel McKennan, Kohrs' friend and president of Helena's Union Bank and Trust Company, replaced Kohrs as director of the Conrad Kohrs Company after his death; Anna Boardman, Kohrs' daughter succeeded John Bielenberg. Kohrs and Bielenberg Realty was sold to the Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company in 1909 and was dissolved in 1919. The Pioneer Placer Mining Company was sold to the holding company in 1923. In 1930 the Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company charter of incorporation expired, and its holdings were transferred to the Conrad Kohrs Company.
On February 23, 1868, Kohrs married Augusta Kruse (1849-1943), a German immigrant who had come to the United States in 1866. They had three children: Anna Catherine (1868-1924), Katharine Christine (1870-1958), and William Kruse Conrad (1879-1901). Conrad Kohrs died on July 23, 1920. John Bielenberg died on June 16, 1922. In 1972 Kohrs' grandson, Conrad Kohrs Warren (b. August 16, 1907) sold the home ranch and outbuildings and 216 acres to the National Park Service, which created the Grant-Kohrs Ranch National Historic Site.
John N.W. Bielenberg was born in the Duchy of Holstein on May 1, 1846, to Claus and Gesche Krause Kohrs Bielenberg. He immigrated to Davenport, Iowa, with his parents in 1854. In 1864 he moved to the Deer Lodge valley of Montana Territory where he became associated with Conrad Kohrs in ranching. In 1909 he was elected to the Senate of the Montana Legislative Assembly from Powell County. He was director of the Union Bank and Trust Company of Montana in Helena and one of the original directors of the Deer Lodge Bank & Trust Company of Deer Lodge.
The Kohrs and Bielenberg Records include three subgroups. The Kohrs and Bielenberg Subgroup contains interoffice correspondence (1913-1920) between Bielenberg and Conrad Kohrs, primarily dealing with business matters, and financial records (1892-1918) pertaining to the Deer Lodge ranch operation. The Conrad Kohrs Estate Subgroup consists of general correspondence (1920-1928) chiefly to and from Samuel McKennan, executor of the estate; and financial records (1920-1928) pertaining to properties held by the estate. The John N.W. Bielenberg Estate Subgroup consists of general correspondence (1924-1927) of the executors Samuel McKennan and R.O. Kaufman and others, court papers (1922-1927), financial records (1922-1927), legal documents (1921-1922), and miscellany (1922-1926). A list of maps transferred to the Library is included in each subgroup.
Arranged by subgroup and series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
Maps have been separated to the Library. See inventory below for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Kohrs and Bielenberg Land and Livestock Company
Beveridge Block (Helena, Mont.); Denver Block (Helena, Mont.); Kohrs Block (Helena, Mont.); Kohrs Ranch (Deer Lodge, Mont.); Helena (Mont.)--Commerce; Treacy Block (Helena, Mont.)
German Americans--Montana--Powell County; Ranches--Montana--Powell County; Land companies--Montana--Helena
Montana; Agriculture; Business, Industry, and Labor
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Kohrs and Bielenberg
  - Interoffice Correspondence
    - John Bielenberg to Conrad Kohrs, 1918, 1920 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Conrad Kohrs to John N.W. Bielenberg, 1913-1917 (Box-folder 1 / 2-3)
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1908-1920 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Financial Records
    - General journal, 1900-1906 (Volume 1)
    - Ledger ("Kohrs and Bielenberg"), 1892-1901 (Volume 2)
    - Index to "Kohrs and Bielenberg" ledger, 1892-1901 (Volume 3)
    - Tax receipts, 1918 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Maps
    - List of Maps transferred to the Library (Box-folder 1 / 6)
- Conrad Kohrs Estate
  - General Correspondence
    - William Anderson, 1920 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - A (correspondents include Don T. Albee; Anaconda National Bank; Anaconda Copper Mining Company; Dave Anderson; The Arco Company; C.N. Arnett), 1922-1926 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - William Biggs and Company, 1920-1926 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - B (correspondents F.W. Bacorn; Noel R. Banks; Baxtur Furniture Company; A.F. Bayes; Fred W. Beatty; Frank C. Beck; Walter Beck; Charles Bell; Walter M. Bickford; Bien and Ross; Blaine County; Anna Boardman; Bonner Lumber Company; Bradstreet Company; E.N. Brandegee; Brenner Livestock Company; J.M. Briggeman; Ross Brown; Dick Buck; Phil Buckley; O.E. Burns; W.J. Butler; Miles Blunt), 1921-1927 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Cook and Cooper Ranch (E.C. Cook and Leslie L. Cooper), 1926-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - C (correspondents include Carl B. Calvin; R.H. Carr; Elmer C. Chambers; Carl Christenson; China R. Clarke; H.W. Cole; William Coleman; Frank Conley; Conley and McTague; A.B. Cook; Guy Crandal; The Crescent Paint and Manufacturing Company; Crowley Brothers), 1920-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Deering - Hauberg Company (enclosing property documents), 1920-1923 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - O.B. DeMott (Kohrs and Bielenberg Ranch), 1923-1927 (Box-folder 1 / 14-15)
    - D-E (correspondents include Deer Lodge Bank and Trust Company; J. Maurice Dietrich; Deer Lodge County; Deer Lodge Farms Company; Deer Lodge Hotel; Deer Lodge Lumber Company; A.R. Deschamps; H.D. Dingwall; C.M. Dorsett; Drake Hotel Company; R.G. Dun and Company; Phil T. Dunn; Charles Ellis; Equitable Life Assurance Society; H.B. Evans; C.T. Evans; Henry W. Evans), 1920-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - Ferris and Hargrove ( E.B. Sherman), 1924 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
    - First State Bank, Wolf Point, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
    - Frye and Company, 1923-1926 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
    - F-G (correspondents include Faddis and Spear; The First National Bank of Wibaux; First National Bank; B. Fischer and Company Inc.; Irving Forst; William Gallagher; Gallatin County; Joseph Ganguet; E.D. Gannt; P.D. Gibbons; Charles Grilk; M.S. Gunn), 1920-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
    - Hanover National Bank, 1924 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
    - J.G. Hodge, 1924-1926 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
    - H-J (correspondents include Harris Trust and Savings Bank; F. M. Heinrichs; The City of Helena; Henningsen Land Company; L.G. Herman; John Herman; J.G. Hodge; A.L. Houston; Huff and Cook; Frank E. Hughes; Wallis Huidekoper; F.S. Jacobsen; F.S. Jacobsen; Frank Jacoby and Son; Johns-Manville; Dr. H.L. Jones), 1921-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
    - Keiley Brothers, 1923-1924, 1928 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
    - Perry Kline (Kohrs and Bielenberg Ranch), 1923, 1926 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
    - Kohrs Packing Company, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
    - K (correspondents include John Kain; Kain Granite Company; Keeley and Keeley; Virgil Kelson; J.E. Kiehl; James Kirkpatrick; Gus Knapp; August Knapp; M.E. Knowles; Knowles Veterinary Supply Company; Augusta Kohrs; John Kopp Jr.; F.C. Krieg Agency), 1922-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
    - George Lane and Company, 1923-1927 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
    - Larabie Brothers Bankers, 1922-1928 (Box-folder 1 / 29)
    - Charles R. Leonard, 1921-1926 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - L (correspondents include Charles Lepley; George M. Lewis; Livingston Publishing Company; The Livingston Enterprise; L.E. Flint; Lost Lake Livestock Company), 1923-1926 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - W.P. McComas c/o Kohrs Ranch, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - McCone County offices: McCone County Abstract Company, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - James Meany (Kohrs-Bielenberg Ranch), 1923-1924 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - M (correspondents include Madison County; William Mannix; Maryland Casualty Company; Masonic Temple Association; A.J. McDonald; C.J. McNamara; Antonne Menard; Metals Bank and Trust Company; Thomas Metcalf; A.B. Middleton; T.B. Miller; Miners Savings Bank and Trust Company; State of Minnesota; Missoula Trust and Savings Bank; E. Mittelstaedt; Ernest Monfortin; Monroe and Son; Montana State Board of Equalization; Montana Treasurer; D.H. Morgan; J.E. Morse; Mueller and Wells), 1920-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - Nels Nelson, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - N-O (correspondents include New York Life Insurance Company; J.A. O'Neill), 1920-1925 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - William J. Paul (Scharnikow and Paul), 1922-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - W.J. Paul, 1924-1926 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - A.S. Pederson, 1926-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - Powell County offices, 1922-1926 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - David Price, 1922-1927 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - P-R (correspondents include Park County; J.O. Patterson; William and Pauly; Carl Peterson; Powell Motors Company; Race Track Creek; A.D. Raymond; W.L. Reed; Charles S. Rhoades; Hermann Riemann; Albert E. Ritchie; E. H. Rollins and Sons; Rosenbaum Brothers and Company; Royal Mining Company; E.B. Ryan), 1920-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - Edward Scharnikow, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
    - Edward Scharnikow (Scharnikow and Paul), 1923-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 16-17)
    - Francis J. Slaughter, 1922-1926 (Box-folder 2 / 18-19)
    - Stapp Motor Car Company, 1927 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
    - S (correspondents include John Schluger; Walter Schurch; J.R. Scott Poultry Farm; Ralph W. Selkirk; R.F. Shanley; Simpson and Truitt; Fred C. Smith; Richard H. Smith; Smith-Yyner Company; Jesse D. Smith; Society of Montana Pioneers; H.A. Streeter), 1922-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
    - Nels Tolan, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 2 / 22-23)
    - T (correspondents include James A. Talbett; Fred Tallon; Fred Thies; Lester Thompson; Thompson's Anxiety Herefords; Edward Toomey; Herman Topel; Thomas Topping; Thomas Topping Company), 1923-1927 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
    - US Internal Revenue Service, 1921-1927 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - United States National Bank of Deer Lodge, 1923-1926 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - U (correspondents include Union Savings Bank; Union-Davenport Trust and Savings Bank; United States Fidelity And Guaranty Company; United States Department of Agriculture; United States Land Office; United States Veterans Bureau), 1920-1926 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Wells-Dickey Company, 1924 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
    - Frederick D. Whisler, 1921-1928 (Box-folder 3 / 5-6)
    - S.P. Wilson, 1922-1927 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - W (correspondents include Alex Walker; Pat Wall; M.J. Wallace; Warren Refining and Chemical Company; The Western Montana National Bank; John Wiener; E.B. Williams Jr., Roy Williams; Perey Williamson; Burl S. Wilson; George B. Winston; Martin Wehlers; William Woods; E.B. Worley), 1920-1927 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Financial Records
    - Annual Report - Beveridge Block, 1920, 1922, 1924 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
    - Receipts and Disbursements, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 3 / 10-11)
    - Receipts - Domestic Laundry, 1921-1923 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
    - Receipts - Helena Properties (Sampling), 1925-1928 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
    - Receipts and Disbursements - Higgins Block, 1920-1926 (Box-folder 3 / 14-20)
    - Receipts and Disbursements - Higgins Block, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 4 / 1-4)
    - Receipts - Kohrs Ranch Deer Lodge (Samplings), 1923-1926, 1928 (Box-folder 4 / 5-9)
    - Receipts and Disbursements - Treacy Block, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 4 / 10)
    - Receipts - Miscellaneous, 1920-1928 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
    - Tax Receipts, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 4 / 12-15)
    - Tax Receipts, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 5 / 1-5)
  - Maps
    - Maps transferred to Library (Box-folder 5 / 6)
- John N.W. Bielenberg Estate
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondents include Edward Scharnikov; S.P. Wilson; Larabie Brothers Bankers; Union Bank and Trust Company; George B. Winston; S.P. Wilson; R.D. Miller; Scharnikow and Paul; W.J. Paul; G.A. Kelley; M.F. Hayes; Charles Grilk; Kohrs Packing Company; Frank Kohrs; Union Savings Bank and Trust Company, 1924-1927 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Court Papers
    - In the Matter of the Estate of John N.W. Bielenberg, 1924-1927 (Box-folder 5 / 8-12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1922-1923, undated (Box-folder 5 / 13-14)
  - Financial Records
    - Cancelled Checks, 1922-1927 (Box-folder 5 / 15)
    - Estate Inventories, 1923-1927 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
    - Taxes, 1922 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements, 1922-1927 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
    - Inventories, 1926 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Last Will and Testament, 1921 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - Probate Registers, 1923-1927 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
  - Maps
    - List of Maps Transferred to the Library (Box-folder 6 / 7)
  - Miscellany
    - Miscellaneous documents regarding John N.W. Bielenbergs Estate, 1922-1926 (Box-folder 6 / 8)